The history that we were all taught
growing up is wrong. My name is Scott
Wolter, and I'm a forensic geologist.
There's a hidden history that nobody
knows about.
There are pyramids, chambers, tombs,
descriptions. They're all over the
world.
We're going to investigate these
artifacts and sites, and we're going to
get to the truth.
Sometimes history isn't what we've been
told.
I'm on my way to Hawaii to investigate
just how far one of the world's most
intrepid groups of voyagers traveled.
I'm not talking about the Vikings or
anyone from Europe. I'm talking about
the Polynesians. We know they settled
Hawaii, but they may have gone even
farther east than that. Maybe even to
what's now the United States mainland.
My investigation starts with an email
from a student in Maui.
>> Aloha, Scott. I'm a college student in
Hawaii, and my archaeology professor
just told me about a spear point some
hikers found in Haleakala National Park,
a volcanic crater here.
Scientists have long been looking for
evidence that the Polynesians not only
settled islands like Hawaii, but
actually made it to the Americas around
1,000 AD.
I think this spear point could be that
evidence, and that's why I'm hoping you
can come take a look. Sean Beckman.
>> The Polynesians were some of the world's
most accomplished sea voyagers.
Most people know very little about them
and their amazing accomplishments.
Hawaii is just one of many islands the
Polynesians settled in the Polynesian
Triangle,
an area of the Pacific the size of
Russia.
Because Hawaii was formed by volcanic
eruptions 400,000 years ago, you'd
expect to find a lot of obsidian
volcanic glass here.
Actually, there isn't much, and what is
here is black.
The spear point in the email Sean sent
is greenish gold,
and I don't think there's any obsidian
in Hawaii that looks like that.
I'm headed to one of the only places on
the islands where obsidian can be found
to talk to an archaeologist.
I want to find out if this artifact
could have come from here,
or if someone, maybe the Polynesians,
brought it here from somewhere else.
>> Scott Walter?
>> Yes.
>> Hi, it's Janet 6.
>> Nice to meet you. Hey, I'm anxious to
see this spear point.
>> I don't have it with me. It's on Maui
with the uh people that found it, but I
do have some photographs here and I'd
like to share with you.
>> Wow.
Well, Janet, this definitely looks like
obsidian and I did find a few pieces of
obsidian here. And obsidian is a
silica-rich volcanic rock that comes out
of a volcano, cools very quickly into a
glass. Is there a lot of obsidian here
in uh Hawaii?
>> Just maybe a couple of quarries. This is
the main quarry that I'm aware of. I was
really interested in the color. And when
I talked to a rock expert, he said,
"Green gold obsidian, that sounds like
Pachuca, which is located in modern-day
Mexico, which at one time was the
ancient homeland of the Olmec and the
Maya."
>> In the New World.
>> Yes. We think that this might have come
from there and I'm doing some analysis
and we're going to see if it's a match
to Pachucan quarry. We know through oral
history that the Polynesians and
Hawaiians went to what they call the
land of mist and frogs.
>> The land of mist and frogs is part of
Hawaiian legend. It's believed to be
what is known as Mesoamerica, Mexico and
Central America before Spanish explorers
arrived.
>> I wouldn't be surprised if the
Polynesians went there and saw a piece
of shiny green gold obsidian that they
wouldn't bring it back with them.
>> So, what you're saying is the
Polynesians would have to be involved
and that would mean that they had to go
there, get this item, make it or trade
for it, then bring it here. Is that
right?
>> Well, we know the Mayans weren't sailing
around the Pacific and we know the
Polynesians were. They're bringing with
them their thoughts, their ideas, things
that are sacred, things that are special
and rocks would have been one of those
things.
>> Maybe a point like this?
>> Could be.
>> Now, can you tell me a little bit about
how this was found and when was it
found?
>> Well, it was found in 2009 by some
friends of mine that were hiking in
Haleakala Crater. And I have some
footage that they actually shot of them
finding it.
They shot this video moments after
recovering this artifact while climbing.
>> So, this little thing here
>> See it there? That thing is big.
And there's Trevor. He's the gentleman
that actually found it. They called the
park and the park kind of poo-pooed the
idea that you would find a giant spear
point inside the park because as we
know, Polynesians don't have that.
>> Right.
>> So, they put it in a box and they didn't
do anything with it.
You can see that steep vertical face.
>> steep, yeah. And it's rugged terrain,
right?
>> adds to the mystery. Who put it there? I
mean, it's not a place you'd leave an
artifact, a simple easy access place.
And so, this begs the question, could
Polynesians have put it there?
>> I'd really like to meet these guys. Is
there any chance I could meet them and
take a look at the artifact?
>> Yeah, I'm sure I can arrange a meeting
for you.
>> Janet, I'm very excited to meet your
friends and see this spear point. But
before I do that, I want to learn more
about the Polynesians. This spear point
could prove that the Polynesians made it
to Mexico. And if they made it that far,
maybe they even made it as far as the
United States.
People may not realize that the Hawaiian
island chain stretches 1,500 mi and
actually includes more than 130 separate
islands.
We know the Polynesians settled this
chain and every island in the Polynesian
triangle before Columbus ever set sail.
They covered that distance in just 400
years between 1000 and 1400 AD.
But, did they go further?
When a couple of hikers in Maui came
upon a spear point made of green gold
obsidian, a type of rock not found here,
they may have stumbled upon evidence the
Polynesians sailed to Mexico and back.
And if these intrepid voyagers could
make that journey, they could easily
have made it to what's now the United
States.
Before I look at this mysterious spear
point, I'm meeting a professor who knows
all about the Polynesians to see what he
thinks about the likelihood that they
made the trip.
Hi Terry.
>> Hi Scott. Welcome.
>> Hey, nice to see you. Thanks for meeting
with me.
>> Sure. I hope you're hungry. I got us
lunch.
>> Chicken looks great.
>> Good.
>> I'd really like to know more about the
Polynesians.
>> Well, Polynesia is a a vast area,
millions of square miles. Most of it, of
course, open ocean with tiny islands.
And Polynesians, over the space of about
a century, about 1200 AD, went from
Tahiti and discovered just about every
single island, all the way to places
like Hawaii, down to New Zealand, out to
Easter Island.
>> Do you think the Polynesians made it to
the New World? And if so, what evidence
do you have?
>> Yes, they did make it to the New World.
And the evidence is right there, sweet
potato. It's not native to Hawaii.
It's the best evidence we have that
there was contact between South America
and Polynesia.
>> You're claiming that the Polynesians
went to South America and brought the
potato back. But a skeptic could argue
that maybe the the floated over, or
somebody else brought it to the islands.
>> The real clincher in the evidence is the
name. The Polynesian word for the sweet
potato is kumara.
And the South American word for the
sweet potato is kumar.
Found in the languages in Ecuador and
Peru. It's a very similar word for the
same thing. Evidence that there was
face-to-face human transfer of this
important crop.
>> Is there anything else, any other
evidence that you can build upon with
the sweet potato?
>> The chicken.
Some believe that the South American
chickens are actually from Polynesia.
Archaeologists have found chicken bones,
and they've dated the chicken bones, and
it does fit just barely within
pre-Columbian times.
So, it may have been chickens from
Polynesia reach South America, sweet
potatoes from South America come back to
Polynesia.
>> Is that the reason we're having our
chicken and our potatoes here for lunch,
or
>> Polynesian food, and this is genuinely
Polynesian. It has been for a long time.
>> Well, Terry, you seem pretty confident
that the Polynesians definitely made it
to South America and back. Do you think
that they could have made it to North
America prior to Columbus?
>> North America wouldn't be that hard to
reach.
Some of my colleagues think that there's
a connection between the Chumash of
California and the Polynesians.
>> The Chumash are a group of Native
American tribes in Southern California
who lived and continued to live along
the coast.
Diseases introduced by Europeans caused
the Chumash population to drop from
22,000 to 300 in a century's time.
There are now 7,000 Chumash living in
the United States.
>> In the Chumash language, you have words
similar to those in Polynesia.
Some believe that there's a linguistic
tie. The same argument, the idea that
there are canoes in California that look
like Polynesian canoes.
>> Terry one thing's for sure.
If there is evidence that the
Polynesians made it to what is now the
United States before Columbus, that
would change history.
>> If you're interested in the California
Polynesia connection, I would say go to
Santa Barbara and learn about the
Chumash evidence. See what you think.
>> I will do that, but not until I finish
my Polynesian chicken
>> Absolutely.
>> and potatoes.
So far, I've learned about an obsidian
spear point ancient Polynesians could
have picked up in Mexico and left here
in Hawaii.
I also found out what great navigators
the Polynesians were, colonizing islands
all over the Pacific in just a few
hundred years.
Not only that, it looks like these
voyagers may have transported food and
language during their travels.
I wonder if the Polynesians made it to
what's now the United States mainland.
Distance-wise, it's actually a shorter
distance to travel from Hawaii to
California than from Hawaii to Mexico.
There are some promising leads to follow
up on in California, but first I'm going
to meet Trevor Carter and Brian Axe.
The guys who found the mysterious spear
point in Mount Haleakala, an inactive
volcano on Maui.
Haleakala is one of the biggest dormant
volcanoes in the world. There's a 2,700
ft drop from rim to crater, and the
distance around Haleakala measures 20
mi.
The volcano last erupted in 1790.
It's a sacred place for all Hawaiians,
and its name means house of the sun.
Yeah, I'm looking for Brian and Trevor.
>> They're on the other side of the ravine.
Um you got two choices. You either take
the long way or the short way.
>> Short way.
Trevor?
>> Scott.
>> How you doing, man?
>> Brian.
>> Aloha.
>> All right. Hey, I'm anxious to see this
spear point. I can't wait. But I want to
hear the story. How'd you find it?
>> It was in 2009 in May. A group of about
12 of us all went up together to do the
15 miles through the crater.
>> Wow.
>> We were all taking a break. Trevor went
off and continued on up the trail. Just
happened to literally step over this
pile of rocks and this rock just really
stood out. And I reached down for it not
thinking anything of it and realizing,
"Hey, this is a piece of obsidian." And
as I got some of the mud off of it, I
realized this is something that's
man-made. As I'm holding this
spearhead,
I just was enthralled by it. The energy
that it put off
wasn't normal.
>> We realized like, "Holy cow, this is
something awesome."
>> It was green, not black obsidian.
>> Well, I've seen some obsidian here just
recently and it's black.
>> Yeah.
>> Sounds like this is different and if
it's different that means it's not from
Hawaii. So you knew that this crater was
a sacred place, right? To the local
people. So you knew it had some
importance to it.
What happened when you went to the park
people? You showed it to them, right?
>> Not immediately cuz the park was closed
and there was no one at the station. We
brought it home and I called the next
morning
and I'm like, "Hey, we found a spearhead
in the crater. What do I do?"
And the official response was
"Well, that doesn't sound Hawaiian.
You're welcome to bring it up. Somebody
will take a look at it and get back to
you maybe."
>> So Trevor, when you found this thing,
did you realize how significant it was?
>> Yeah. I actually got a tattooed on my
side. I have it permanently on me right
now.
>> You did?
>> I did.
>> I got to see it.
>> All right.
>> Ha.
Look at that.
What does it say here?
>> It means gift of the warrior spirit.
>> So you assumed that this thing was made
here in Hawaii with Hawaiian obsidian,
right?
>> That's what I thought. I didn't know
anything else because I didn't really
know the history of this area.
>> Well Trevor, I love the tattoo.
>> Thanks.
>> But I'd like to see the real thing.
Let's take a look.
>> Scott, I have really bad news.
>> What?
>> They took it this last Tuesday before
you got here.
>> What do you mean they took it? Who's
they?
>> The National Park. We don't have it.
>> So are you telling me that the park
service
just took from you this potentially
history-changing artifact? They just
took it?
So are you telling me that the Park
Service
just took from you this potentially
history-changing artifact? They just
took it?
Physically took it from you?
>> We don't have it.
The National Park set up a meeting with
me to actually see it for the first time
in 4 years, and they took it, knowing
that I was meeting with you.
>> You're serious, aren't you?
>> Absolutely.
>> We originally called them the day after
the discovery.
>> Right.
>> They made it seem like
it wasn't of any significance.
>> They didn't care.
>> They made no reference to caring,
whomever I spoke to.
>> Well, why do they care now?
>> I personally believe they care now cuz
they knew you were coming.
>> But, why did they take the artifact? I
don't understand that. Explain that to
me.
>> I don't understand it, either. And we
were together for an hour. I was sharing
photos, everything I had that we have
found over the years.
>> So, it's civil at this point.
>> Completely.
>> Okay, when did it turn? When did they
make the play for the artifact? Did they
say, "We want you to hand it over?"
>> No. They asked me if I had it with me
after about an 45 minutes, and
I took a breath in, and I I said, "Yes,
I do. I do have it."
>> And she demanded the artifact? Is that
what happened?
>> She showed me her badge. It was a
federal law enforcement badge.
I handed her the artifact. I stepped
back. She was threatening to arrest me.
>> What the hell is this?
Seriously,
>> hoodwinked.
>> What I don't understand is I've never
heard of anything like this before. I
mean, I've seen things covered up, swept
under the rug. I've seen every excuse in
the world that people can think of to
cover up an artifact, to try to show
this isn't real, it's fake. But, I have
never heard of a sting operation like
this. This is crazy.
>> They had no interest in just blowing off
a couple guys, and then realized maybe
this is significant, maybe this has some
worth and value to history, and they
want in on it. All we really wanted is
for this artifact to get studied and get
the attention that it deserves.
>> Well, I think it's going to get the
attention it deserves. I just wish it
would have happened in a different way.
Janet Six showed me a couple of photos.
You guys have to have some photos.
>> They're back at the car. We're going to
have to take the long way back, but I
got a bunch.
>> The fact that the National Park Service
confiscated the obsidian spear point 4
years after Trevor found it tells me
it's even more important than I thought.
It's illegal to take artifacts found on
National Park's property, but it sounds
to me like these guys tried to do the
right thing.
Keeping artifacts in their
archaeological context is important so
scientists can study them properly.
The spear point could be evidence the
Polynesians traveled to the New World
before Columbus and brought back a
sacred souvenir.
The key thing here is Janet testing to
find out if they can actually
fingerprint this to quarries over in
Mexico. And if she can do that, boy,
that's to me is really the final test.
Let's see what you have.
>> I got it.
Well, the first photo is a a picture of
the artifact on a piece of paper. It has
the dates, the location, and the primary
witnesses who were on the hike.
>> So, they grabbed this as well as the
artifact.
>> Absolutely. This is some close-ups where
you can see the uniqueness of it
compared to Hawaiian obsidian.
>> Well, it's got that sort of golden glow
along the edges here.
>> That's exactly what we noticed right off
the bat. It's sparked interest all over
the place. We were so fortunate to have
folks from our local NASA Astrophysics
Lab bring us into the office and take
some pictures which
>> Do you have some of those?
>> Let me pull them up right now.
>> Okay.
Well, clearly man-made, probably a
ceremonial piece.
>> You can see that they were skilled in
what they were doing.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> It wasn't machines. It's man-made, but
they knew what they were doing. My
favorite quote from all of the the
people who have looked at this was from
a flint mapping specialist over on the
Big Island. He said, "If this is tourist
junk, this is museum grade tourist
junk."
>> Junk.
I can tell you one thing, guys. This is
not junk. Hang on just one sec here.
Getting a text from somebody.
Hi Scott.
Got the detailed data back on the spear
point. The green gold obsidian is, in
capital letters, from Pachuca, like we
thought.
Could be evidence the Polynesians got to
Mexico and back. Janet.
>> Well, you needed some good news, that's
for sure.
>> Yeah, that's an understatement.
>> There's no way this spear point came
from Haleakala crater. They don't have
obsidian like that.
Guys, I have to go up and talk to them.
>> I don't know if it's going to do you any
good.
>> You can't go up there.
>> So, they won't let me up there?
>> They said none of us were allowed up
there until this investigation is
finished.
>> Well, then we'll have to find another
way to get to the truth.
I came to Hawaii to find out if an
out-of-place spear point could be the
key to unlocking the mystery of whether
Polynesian navigators made it to the New
World long before Columbus.
Here's what I have so far. The
discovered spear point is made of
obsidian that can't be found in Hawaii.
It's believed it came from a quarry in
Mexico. Janet, the archaeologist, had it
tested and incredibly, it was a match.
The theory is Polynesian voyagers went
to Mexico and brought the spear point
back here to Hawaii.
Unfortunately, I'm only able to see
pictures of it since the artifact itself
was confiscated.
But, the spear point isn't the only
piece of evidence to suggest that around
1000 AD, the same time Vikings were
discovering America in the north,
the Polynesians may have been setting
foot on the other side of the continent.
I'm meeting an archaeologist named Terry
Jones in Santa Barbara, who claims to
have the next clue in this
investigation.
Hi Terry, Scott Walter.
>> Scott, nice to meet you.
>> Nice to meet you. I see you've got a
canoe behind you. Tell me a little bit
about this.
>> Our local Chumash, our Native Americans
here in Southern California, brought a
modern replica of a tomol.
>> Okay.
>> Which is a sewn plank canoe. What's
unique about it, what's important about
it, is the engineering, the way it's
constructed.
>> You have a plank here.
You have a seam.
And then another redwood plank.
>> Mhm.
>> And then they're sewn together at a
number of locations, and the craft is
built up with this combination of sewn
planks and then a tar sealer to keep it
watertight.
>> That's amazing. It's really
sophisticated. So, how does this canoe
construction technique connect with the
Polynesians?
>> This was the standard technique for
making boats
among Polynesians. And I have an example
right here.
>> Okay.
So, this is the Polynesian style.
>> Here you can see the same technique.
>> You've got virtually the same
shipbuilding techniques that either
developed independently here in North
America and in Polynesia, or there had
to have been some type of contact.
Correct?
>> That's exactly the way we see it. Now,
it's certainly possible that in both
places they invented the same
technology. However, not only do we have
the same technology, but we have
linguistic similarities. The first one
is the word that refers to this craft.
The ancient word for sewn planks boats
would have been tumala'au. That word is
very, very similar linguistically
to a word that we would have seen in
Polynesia, tumuraka'u.
>> On paper, these two words may not appear
to share more than a couple of letters,
but linguistics isn't about how words
are spelled, but how they sound.
When pronounced by native Chumash and
native Polynesians, these two words
would have sounded the same.
Is there any other linguistic evidence?
>> There were two groups in Southern
California that used these boats, the
Chumash and the Gabrielino.
The Gabrielino word for their boats is
not tuma'al, it's ti'at. Polynesian word
ti'a is to sew. Sewn plank canoe, to
sew, it seems like it can't be just a
coincidence.
>> Uh I would think not.
But would this canoe have been used to
travel across the ocean?
>> Well, these particular canoes were used
primarily to get out to the islands off
the coast of Southern California. The
Polynesians used this technique to make
much larger boats that also had sails
that allowed them to cover thousands of
miles of open water.
>> Okay.
Is there any other material evidence,
such as stone tools of any kind, that
might provide a connection?
>> We do have some archaeological evidence.
This is a pretty standard shellfish hook
that we see from Southern California.
These things came into existence about
3,000 years ago.
>> Okay.
>> But after about 1300 AD,
we see this much more elaborate style.
It has
a barb, it has a groove for attaching
the line. We see the exact same style
throughout much of Polynesia. We don't
think necessarily that Polynesians came
here and stayed. There was an exchange
of ideas about how to work wood, about
engineering, about how to build boats.
And then they probably left.
>> But they had an impact on each other.
>> They had an impact, they had an effect.
>> And this would be one of the things that
the people here learned.
>> Is there any chance that we might be
able to try this canoe out? Think we're
in luck.
Based on what Terry told me, I think
these paddlers' ancestors may have had a
visit from ancient Polynesian voyagers
who set foot on American soil long ago.
The canoe construction, the linguistics,
the fishhook design, these are all
significant connections.
But what I want to know now is, what do
the Chumash people themselves have to
say about this alleged ancient
connection?
Terry has arranged an introduction with
a Chumash elder to help me understand
this 600-year-old relationship.
>> Scott, I am so happy to be able to
introduce you to my friend Georgiana.
She's a Chumash elder here.
>> Hi Georgiana, nice to meet you.
>> So happy to meet you, Scott.
>> I've been investigating the idea that
Eastern Polynesians may have come here
to what is now Southern California. What
I'd like to talk to you about is oral
tradition. Is there any mention of
contact with Polynesians coming here?
>> There is. My own genealogy goes back to
the island of Limu. People know that
island as Santa Cruz Island.
>> Off the coast here?
>> Off the coast of California, right here.
>> Limu means seaweed. All around Limu are
these big kelp forests and seaweed beds.
>> Mhm.
>> And Limu is a Polynesian word.
>> So, this is a word that your people
picked up
from somewhere?
>> Long, long time ago.
>> Is there anything else you might suggest
I look at that might be able to help me
with this ancient Polynesian connection?
>> Well, have you heard of the Kennewick
Man?
>> I have heard of the Kennewick Man.
You're talking about one of the oldest
skeletons ever found in North America
dating back about 9,000 years ago.
>> Well, I've heard recently
that the Kennewick Man could possibly
have been Polynesian.
>> Polynesian?
>> Yes.
>> Kennewick Man is an ancient skeleton
that was found in Kennewick, Washington
in 1996.
I tracked down the guy who literally
stumbled across it.
His name is Will Thomas and he's taking
me to where he found the skeleton when
he was in college. It was a
controversial find because local tribes
believed the bones were one of their
ancestors. While they fought to have
them reburied, scientists fought in
court for a chance to study the remains
which were dated to sometime around
7,300 BC.
The study of those bones is what caused
the Polynesian connection to surface.
>> All right, you want to give me a hand to
pull this boot up? All right. I'm going
to show you where we found Kennewick
Man. All right. Head over this way.
>> Tell me about this discovery.
>> Well,
Dave and I were
trying to sneak into the boat races,
have a couple of beers before we got in
the races. That's really ultimately what
led to finding Kennewick Man.
>> So, you're sneaking in, then what
happened?
>> So, we were walking along the shoreline,
and we were right about to enter the
spot where you get into the park and the
races. I looked down, and
I see this rock
underwater that looks enough like a head
that I was going to mess with my friend
Dave. So, I I pick up this rock,
and
first thing I see is teeth.
Turns out it is a human head.
Holy crap.
>> We know ancient Polynesians traveled
far. The question is, how far?
Could they have made it to what's now
the US mainland decades, maybe even
centuries before Columbus?
There's a lot of evidence to back that
up.
The out-of-place spear point that
suggests the Polynesians made it to
Mexico and back in the distant past.
Food, boats, fish hooks, and even words
all suggest these intrepid voyagers
traveled to South and North America
around 1,000 AD.
But now, there could be reason to
believe that the ancestors of those
Polynesian voyagers may have been here
far earlier than that, around 9,000
years ago, making them some of the first
people ever to set foot in what's now
the United States.
>> I'm in Kennewick, Washington talking to
Will Thomas, the person who discovered
Kennewick Man, an ancient skeleton which
may be connected to the Polynesians.
Back in '96, Will was just a college kid
trying to sneak into the local boat
races when he made a find that changed
American history.
>> I see this rock
underwater that looks enough like a head
that I was going to mess with my friend
Dave.
So, as soon as I started getting that
thing up out of the water, the first
thing I saw was a set of teeth on it.
So, my rock my rock turned into a skull.
>> was a skull. It was a skull.
>> It was a skull.
>> What happened then?
>> We made the decision to just hide the
skull,
meet our friends at the beer garden. One
of my friends there, he wasn't buying
any of the story.
>> Calling your bluff.
>> So, he says, "I don't believe you. Let's
go see this skull."
So, I said, "All right, let's go." So,
we jumped on his motorcycle, headed to
the site, found the skull,
put the skull under my arm, and we drove
back to the truck and I showed the rest
of my buddies it.
>> This is every archaeologist's worst
nightmare.
>> I can't argue with you.
>> So, you've taken the skull to the
police, they bring the boat over here,
they pull up to shore, then what
happened?
>> They started picking up bones
immediately. Dave and I go over and
check out, see what they're looking at,
and my friend Dave pipes up and says,
"Oh yeah, that's a stick." We had
already found that earlier. And they all
just kind of stopped and
looked at us and they said, "No, this is
a femur off of a human being."
>> Yes.
>> Thigh bone.
>> Yeah.
>> So, when the police were at the site,
they're looking at these bones, did they
know they were old at the time or were
they thinking it was a recent death?
>> They could tell it was old immediately.
They got the radiocarbon dating back on
that. Those bones are over 9,000 years
old. There's a local archaeologist by
the name of Jim Chatters, and he got
involved with Kennewick Man the very
night that we found him.
>> Well, I would like to look at the
skeleton as well. Do you think I could
maybe meet with him?
>> Yeah, well, he might be able to help you
out. He might have a tough time getting
to the bones, however, those are under
lock and key right now at the Burke
Museum in Seattle.
>> Kennewick Man, the skeleton some people
think is connected to ancient
Polynesians, is inside the Burke Museum,
but I can't see him. Nobody can.
The Army Corps of Engineers says
Kennewick Man's skeleton is too fragile
for anyone to touch.
In fact, a team of scientists had to sue
for the right to study him.
I'm on my way to meet one of them, the
guy Will Thomas told me about.
>> Well, welcome to the lab.
>> So, what do we know about Kennewick Man?
What did you learn?
>> He had more injuries than I've ever seen
on anybody except one fellow who'd been
in a helicopter crash in Vietnam,
head-on collision with a truck on his
motorcycle, and then beaten to death by
his neighbor.
That's the worst one I've ever seen, but
Kennewick Man was second to that.
>> So, Kennewick Man must have led a
violent life.
>> You can see here there's a stone spear
point
>> Yeah.
>> that was healed inside the pelvis.
>> This guy's just dealing with pain every
day.
>> He got struck in the chest, probably
right in the center of the chest.
There's a couple breaks here that were
healed.
>> Could he have been rammed by an animal
or something?
>> He could have been rammed by an animal,
he could have fallen off a cliff, any
number of possibilities.
>> This really underscores how much
information you can learn about a
person's life just by looking at their
skeleton. It's amazing. Jim, I would
really like to be able to see this
skeleton, especially the skull.
>> No. No, the Kennewick man won't allow
anyone to see it.
>> How about a CAT scan of the skull? Has
that taken place?
>> Yeah, in 2005 when we had the authorized
studies.
>> You know, I think I have an idea.
Since I can't get my hands on the real
Kennewick man to look for a Polynesian
connection, I'm going to do the next
best thing.
Using data from a CAT scan, I'm going to
make a 3D print of Kennewick man's skull
at the University of Washington to
compare with a cast of a Native American
skull.
When compared to Native Americans,
Polynesians have longer skulls, more
elongated facial features, and wider
cheekbones.
Hey Dwayne, how you doing?
>> I'm good, Scott. Good to see you.
>> Yeah. This is my friend Jim.
>> Hi Dwayne, how are you?
>> Tell us how it works.
>> We're going to take the CT scan data,
convert it into an appropriate file
format, and then we're going to print it
slice by slice on a powder printer.
>> Well, it's like printing multiple pages,
only stacking them on top of each other
and gluing them together.
>> It's exactly that. Yes. Each layer is
about 4,000ths of an inch, so you can
think of it roughly like a sheet of
paper.
>> What are some of the applications that
3D printing is typically used for, and
what what can you use it for?
>> It's starting to become used in
biomedical applications, you know, in
extreme cases, say somebody loses an ear
in a fire, but I can scan the other ear,
mirror it,
print a replacement part for a
prosthetic.
>> Amazing.
>> There's also just fun things you can do
with 3D printing. We did a project in
class last year where everybody got 3D
scanned and we produced little mini me
figures.
>> Is that you?
>> That's me.
>> That's incredible.
How long is this going to take?
>> Printing a full-size skull should take
about a 12-hour print time and then
we'll let it sit overnight. It'll be
ready to depowder in the morning.
>> I'm ready to get started.
>> Let the 3D printing begin.
I think we're all set up. We've got it
oriented in the build space.
>> How did it go?
>> Well, the computer thinks that it
completed the build, but you never
really know until you pull it out.
>> So, the real test is let's see what we
got.
>> Exactly. You can just start
sweeping.
So, you just want to go gently through
there until we
find something that's bound together.
>> Something's appearing right here.
>> That's what we're looking for.
>> Yeah, you guys There it is. Teeth, nice
nose.
>> Right. Look at
Oh.
This is awesome. There's the skull.
There's the eyes. Jim, does this look
familiar?
>> Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. He looks familiar
from beginning of the nose.
Everything we
need for comparison is
pretty much there. Yeah, I brought that
cast of a Native American with me. I can
>> All right.
Point out the differences here. What
makes these two different from each
other? I mean, I can see some subtle
things, but help me out.
>> This one, Kennewick Man, is much longer
and narrow than the Native American one.
He also has this
projecting mid-face. This face projects
forward, whereas this one is more or
less straight up and down. The
cheekbones aren't nearly as wide. See
that there?
>> Okay, yeah.
>> And the face is is much longer here
than it is in in Kennewick Man.
>> Okay.
Longer Longer face. Now, the big
question for me is do we have Polynesian
features here, and is there a connection
with ancient Polynesians?
>> Well, there are 63 measurements we do on
the skull. The statistical analysis
makes Kennewick Man closest to
Polynesians of all the peoples of the
world.
>> To the layman, the differences between
the skulls are subtle, but the Kennewick
Man's skull and the Native American
skull are different.
When you compare them, Kennewick Man's
face is longer,
it jets out forward,
and the cheeks are wider.
But when you compare Kennewick Man's
skull to a Polynesian skull, the results
are scientifically striking in their
similarity.
From the high-tech 3D printer to the
low-tech canoe, the evidence is
overwhelming. I believe Polynesians
traveled to the New World, and they did
it a lot earlier than we thought.
I have learned so much on this
investigation with your help and many
other people. I'm convinced that ancient
Polynesians not only made it to South
America, but North America as well. The
great oceans of the world were far from
barriers. They were actually
superhighways. There's no doubt in my
mind that there were many cultures
coming across the oceans to North
America, not only hundreds of years, but
thousands of years before Christopher
Columbus ever set sail.
My investigation into whether
Polynesians made it to America before
Columbus has taken me from Hawaii
to California and to Washington state in
search of evidence.
I think I found it.
I've discovered that the Polynesians may
have shared things like sweet potatoes,
language, canoe building technology, and
other innovations with people along the
North American and South American
coasts.
Over and over again, I'm struck by how
the things we find today
bones,
stones, and strange symbols connect us
with people from the past.
There's no denying that people in the
Americas have long been
and continue to be
influenced by people across the Pacific
and the Atlantic.
We've discovered so much about the bonds
that connect us,
but I know there's still a lot left to
learn.
>> The history that we were all taught
growing up is wrong.
My name is Scott Wolter, and I'm a
forensic geologist.
There's a hidden history that nobody
knows about.
There are pyramids, chambers, tombs,
descriptions. They're all over the
world.
We're going to investigate these
artifacts and sites, and we're going to
get to the truth.
Sometimes history isn't what we've been
told.
As a forensic geologist, I rely on the
study of rocks to learn more about our
own history.
And throughout my career, there have
been several artifacts that I constantly
return to.
One of them is called the Bat Creek
Stone.
Though small in size, it's considered
one of archaeology's biggest mysteries.
I first learned about it during an
unrelated investigation back in 2008.
I was examining some cave inscriptions
with a woman named Leslie Kaelin when
she told me about the stone and how it's
inscribed with strange writing.
I was immediately intrigued and had to
know more.
The Bat Creek Stone was discovered back
in 1889 in a Native American burial
mound in Loudon County, Tennessee, along
with jewelry and nine human skeletons.
The writing on the stone was first
thought to be a form of Cherokee script.
Later, it was determined to be an
ancient form of Hebrew.
Why would a stone with Hebrew writing be
buried in a Native American mound?
After years of research, a possible
connection began to emerge.
Could the stone be an ancient Hebrew
land claim?
Possibly from the lost tribes of Israel?
The lost tribes of Israel are 10 tribes
that disappeared from the Holy Land in
722 BC after the Assyrians waged a
bloody battle against them.
To this day, no one knows if they died,
escaped, or assimilated into the
population.
Some believe they traveled to America to
build a new Jerusalem.
The Smithsonian officially owns the Back
Creek Stone, but it's housed at the
McClung Museum in Knoxville, Tennessee.
Leslie's father, a Cherokee elder,
helped me get permission to study the
stone, which I examined in 2010.
Now, I'm returning to Tennessee to
examine it using state-of-the-art
technology. I hope looking at it with a
3D microscope will help determine if the
stone is an ancient relic of the lost
tribes of Israel
or something else.
Before my re-examination,
I'm meeting with Leslie Kaelin again to
see what she knows about this mysterious
artifact and any connections between the
lost tribes of Israel and the Native
American site where the stone was found.
So, aside from the inscription, is there
any evidence of an early Hebrew
connection with
people or places in Tennessee?
>> I think that some of my people believe
that we might be descendants from the
lost tribe. My grandfather told me that
he felt that we had a Jewish connection.
Maybe even possibly be part of the lost
tribe of Israel.
There is a group called the Central Band
of Cherokees. They believe that they are
direct descendants
of the lost tribe of Israel.
>> On my way to the Maquoketa Museum, I
can't stop thinking about what Leslie
said.
As a scientist, I focus on facts, but in
this case, I can't ignore the oral
tradition.
If some Cherokee people believe they're
connected to the lost tribes of Israel,
maybe there's something to it.
>> Here it is.
>> All right.
>> fresh off the exhibit for you.
>> I'm really excited to look at the Bat
Creek Stone. With the new technology,
this Keyence 3D microscope that's going
to hopefully help answer the question,
is it authentic or not?
>> And that's part of why you're studying
it. There is some controversy about the
stone.
>> Can you give me just a brief synopsis as
you understand the history of the Bat
Creek Stone?
>> Yeah, it has a very interesting history.
It was part of the Smithsonian's Bureau
of Ethnology's mound survey that Cyrus
Thomas was leading to try to understand
what they call at time the mystery of
the mound builders of who actually built
these things. And one of those
excavations was done in Loudon County,
Tennessee at the intersection of Bat
Creek with the Little Tennessee River.
And excavate a couple of mounds there
and one of them was a burial mound where
they actually found the Bat Creek Stone.
>> A scientist named Cyrus Thomas was in
charge of the mound survey.
Initially, he thought the mounds were
the work of some advanced race which no
longer existed.
Eventually, he went on record with his
belief that the Cherokee people were
somehow connected to the prehistoric
mound builders.
Some critics believe John Emmert, the
field archaeologist working on the
project who found the Bat Creek Stone,
may have planted the artifact to get in
good with his boss.
>> He was actually at one point fired from
the Smithsonian and was rehired and this
was one of his first projects after
being rehired. Did that actually
influence him in in what he did or
didn't do? And that we'll never know.
Beyond Bat Creek Stone, there are other
stone tablets and other things that
clearly
>> They were hoaxes. You have found fakes.
>> There are things out there.
>> I have found fakes, but I have also
found things like the Kensington
Runestone is absolutely genuine.
The Bat Creek Stone is one of the
classic examples of bad science run
amok.
Everybody's got an opinion.
>> Mhm.
>> And you know what they're worth in many
cases.
The rocks don't have bad days. They
don't care. They just are. So, we go
back to the science and I always say I
let the rocks talk.
>> The Bat Creek Stone was found in a
Native American burial mound in the
1880s.
Some people think it's a hoax.
They suspect the guy who found the stone
faked its inscription to get in good
with his boss at the Smithsonian.
I'm not buying that.
I think the stone may prove Jewish
people made it to America before
Columbus.
This artifact could even be connected to
the lost tribes of Israel.
They're famous for vanishing without a
trace in 722 BC.
Some Cherokee people in Tennessee think
they have a connection to the lost
tribes.
I've studied the Bat Creek Stone once,
but now I'm back in Tennessee to examine
it with the latest technology.
If I can figure out how old the carvings
are on the stone using 3D analysis, it
would go a long way towards solving the
lost tribes mystery.
I want to show you something here that I
think is pretty important. This is the
very first picture taken of the Bat
Creek Stone, 1894.
If you look in this area right here,
there are no scratches.
>> Right.
>> But,
in this 1971 photograph, you can see
there are two scratches.
>> Clearly.
>> Clearly they were added after the stone
was found.
>> Right.
>> Do you have any thoughts on why that
might have happened or how that may have
happened?
>> Well, I mean, there's two things that
could happen. Could have been
accidentally scratched in some form or
fashion, or it could be somebody trying
to do some sort of early testing before
3D imaging to see what it's made of and
how easy it is to scratch and things
like that. We will do some test
scratches like that sometimes.
>> What's important about this is these
serve as excellent control samples for
me to compare with the original
inscription to see if they're the same.
>> Hopefully this machine can tell us some
more today.
We start by examining the modern
scratch.
I'm not sure if this mark was made
accidentally or on purpose. It doesn't
matter. What does matter is that this
scratch may be able to help prove the
authenticity of the Bat Creek stone.
>> When they scratch the stone, it will
generate secondary material that's left
behind.
And we see that here in the freshly
scratched surface.
>> Whenever you scratch a stone, you leave
stuff behind, deposits from making the
mark. The fact that we see residue in
this microscopic view speaks to the fact
that this is a recent carving.
Because we're looking at a recent
scratch, it would make sense some of
that material is still there.
>> No polish marks.
>> Clearly rough. I mean, it's uh something
that was intentional, but uh not be
beautiful.
>> Yes.
So, let's take a look at the original
inscription. If it was fresh like the
scratch, we would see secondary material
in there, and we don't see that.
Well, as you can see here, we don't have
any of those deposits that we saw on the
fresh scratch. They're completely gone.
It's clean as a whistle. It's completely
weathered away. The weathering is key
because
to get that weathering profile took
time. We've got nice rounded edges, and
the polished surface
looks nothing like the fresh scratch.
>> Right.
>> In Emmert's notes, the first time he
mentions the stone, he said it was a
polished stone. You can see the
scratches going into the grooves after
it was carved. So, clearly that
indicates the inscription was carved
first, then it was polished.
The inscription on the Bat Creek Stone
was clearly polished, unlike those new
scratches, which weren't polished at
all.
>> By polishing it, that tells you that
they're treating this with care, that it
has meaning to them, and maybe even
sacred.
>> If Emmert faked the inscription, it
would look newer, more like the modern
scratches, but the inscription looks
really old.
>> So, here's the question for you.
Can that be faked?
>> You can make a charge that somebody did
something anytime you want, but making
it stick is the key thing.
We've talked a lot about the
inscription, but we haven't really
talked about what it says. One of the
top Semitic scholars in the world at
that time has translated the inscription
as for the Judaeans.
>> The Judaeans were a Jewish people who
occupied a mountainous region called
Judaea, which today is Israel's West
Bank and the northern Negev Desert.
The region was named after the biblical
tribe of Judah, one of the lost tribes
of Israel.
If the Bat Creek Stone really does bear
the inscription for the Judaeans, it
could be a significant clue that
suggests the lost tribes came to
America.
>> There's been some other interpretation
as well, but nothing too drastically
different. How old do you think that is?
How much older do you think that is than
those modern scratches?
>> The type of work that I do is what I
call relative age dating. It's older
than this, it's younger than that. We
know this is this old, we know this is
this old, it's in between, so it has to
fall somewhere in the middle.
By looking at the weathering of the
original inscription, comparing it with
the modern scratches, to me that says it
wasn't made during modern times. Emmert
said he pulled it from the mound. I've
seen no evidence to question that. The
other thing I think that's very
important is this double-barred cross of
Lorraine, which was used by early Jewish
groups and is a symbol of the
crucifixion. That would not be
consistent with the lost tribes of
Israel if it represented the
crucifixion. I mean, we're talking about
a group that disappeared around 700 BC
and the crucifixion obviously is is
800 years later in this particular case.
>> Yeah, obviously
wrong time.
>> After taking a closer look at the cross
of Lorraine, I still don't have enough
information to definitively connect the
lost tribes of Israel with the Bat Creek
Stone.
Still, this is a mysterious artifact
with Hebrew on it. I've looked at
others, too. They make me wonder who
created them, when, and why.
>> I'm very comfortable that the Bat Creek
Stone, all evidence here to me indicates
that it looks to be a genuine artifact.
But there are other artifacts that have
been found in North America,
pre-Columbian artifacts with Hebrew
inscriptions on them.
I've investigated Ohio's Decalogue
Stone.
It has a shortened version of the Ten
Commandments on it, written in
Paleo-Hebrew.
Same story in Los Lunas, New Mexico,
where there's a similar artifact, also
called the Decalogue Stone, with the Ten
Commandments on it.
And in Arizona, more Hebrew on the
Tucson Lead Artifacts, a collection of
authentic ritual objects pulled from the
desert in 1924.
I have to wonder if all these things are
markers on a trail left by Hebrew people
long ago.
>> There's a person that I'm going to go
visit and talk to a little bit more
about the Bat Creek Stone and about some
other artifacts.
>> Part of the the science of all this is
actually having a dialogue and talking
to different scholars, different
perspectives and expertise.
>> We've had a good exchange today.
But now I want to ask you, Tim, are you
convinced by what you've seen here today
that the Bat Creek stone is a genuine
pre-Columbian Hebrew artifact?
Well, Tim, you are the curator here at
the McClung Museum that houses the Bat
Creek stone artifact. We've just spent a
good part of the day looking at brand
new data. So, based on everything you've
seen, do you think that the Bat Creek
stone is a genuine pre-Columbian Hebrew
artifact?
>> I'm not completely convinced yet, but
you did show me some things today I
didn't expect. There's some potential
other things that need to be done before
I can say yes, you have a authentic
stone.
>> But your mind is open.
>> Oh, as a scientist, my mind's always
open.
>> I have to say that I'm convinced this is
a genuine artifact, but I'm all about
collecting more data. I'm going to go
see if I can find some more evidence
of some early Hebrew culture coming to
North America prior to Columbus, long
before Columbus, possibly the lost
tribes of Israel.
I'm on my way to see an artifact expert
named Hugh McCollough. He's studied the
Bat Creek stone and other artifacts
found inside the burial mound.
A while back, Hugh showed me another
allegedly Hebrew artifact called the
Decalogue Stone in Coshocton, Ohio.
Today, we're meeting in another part of
Ohio at a national park known for its
mounds.
Well, Hugh, it's good to see you again.
>> Good to see you, Scott, and welcome to
Ohio.
Tell me what you found in Tennessee. You
didn't say that you looked at the Bat
Creek Stone down there.
>> I had a chance to look at the artifact
with my new technology, the 3D digital
microscope. I was able to confirm that
the weathering of the inscription is
indeed old.
There's no question that the Bat Creek
Stone is not a hoax. It's a genuine
artifact. And the fact that it's
Paleo-Hebrew says to me that it has to
be an early Jewish group that created
it, possibly the lost tribes.
>> Well, I agree it's uh Jewish artifact.
So, I think it's very exciting.
>> Tell me a little bit about the testing
that you did back in the 1980s.
>> There was some wooden ear spools found
with the stone.
>> Wooden ear spools, tell me a little bit,
what are those?
>> The Hopewell and many other cultures use
these ear spools. They're just
decorative ear spools. They stretch the
ears. We were able to get a carbon date
on those. It was somewhere between 32
and 769 AD.
>> So, Hugh, based on the data, it doesn't
look like this is the lost tribes, who
were probably around 722 BC. This is
something more in the first century,
right?
>> If you look at the inscription here,
here's your photo of the Bat Creek
Stone. And the style of the letters most
closely matches that of the Jewish war
coins of the 65 to 70 AD.
The letter style matches almost
perfectly. There would have been an
incentive at that time for Jewish people
to emigrate because
if they stayed behind,
they would have been nailed to a cross
or fed to the lions or enslaved.
>> Around 70 AD, Jews and their Roman
rulers were fighting over unfair
taxation, disrespect for the Jewish
faith, and accusations of theft. The
rebellion known as the Great Revolt was
eventually crushed by the Romans. Four
years later, Jerusalem was captured, and
100,000 Jews were killed or sold into
slavery.
The big question,
did other Jews escape and find their way
to America?
>> There's another piece of evidence here,
too, that jumps out at me is this
double-barred cross. That's probably one
of the earliest, if not the earliest,
versions of the cross of Lorraine. The
cross of Lorraine is symbolic of the
crucifixion, which would have been
sometime in the middle late 1st century,
consistent with an early Jewish group in
the 1st or 2nd century.
>> All the testing that you had done, the
testing of the ear spools, and the
script, all do overlap.
>> About what time?
>> Around the 1st century AD.
>> So, you've got consistency from
different points. Now, we have the
geology work that I've done as far as
the weathering indicating that it's very
old, that it's not a modern hoax.
Based on all of this, we have apparently
a 1st or 2nd century Jewish artifact
found in a Native American Indian mound,
and its historical importance cannot be
overstated.
>> I agree with the ears, Scott, but
there's one more piece of evidence I
want to show you, which is even bigger
in a sense.
>> I'm interested. Let's go.
It's becoming clear to me the Bat Creek
Stone and the ear spools found in the
same burial mound don't go back far
enough to be connected to the lost
tribes of Israel.
I keep wondering, who left these things,
and what does it all mean?
>> So, this is a photocopy of a map that
was made by the US Army Corps of
Engineers 1823 of some earthworks here
in Ohio.
>> Earthworks, also known as mounds, are
intentional changes in land level.
These sculpted piles of rocks and soil
are often ancient, mysterious, and
massive.
>> What does this portion up here look like
to you?
>> Well, that looks like a menorah.
>> Right.
>> Is that what that is?
>> Well, that's what it looks like.
>> The menorah, also called a Hanukkiah, is
the symbol of Hanukkah.
The 8-day Jewish holiday celebrates the
rededication of their temple after years
of fighting.
The Hanukkah story tells how soldiers
who recaptured the temple had only
enough oil for one night, but
miraculously, it lasted for eight.
So, let me get this straight. Somebody
in the distant past built this
earthwork, that's traditionally Native
American, in the shape of a menorah?
>> Well, if we didn't have the Bat Creek
Stone and the Decalogue Stone, I'd
be totally bewildered. A Jewish idea
like this is not so strange after all,
maybe.
>> Experts believe the Hopewell people
built both the Hanukkiah earthworks on
the Army Corps map, as well as all the
mounds surrounding us here at Hopewell
Culture National Park.
>> I mean, that looks like a lamp, an oil
lamp.
>> it looks like the oil lamp that it was
supposed to have burned.
>> What else can it be?
>> can it be?
>> Yeah.
Well, let me ask you this. This is a
beautiful place, but why did you take me
here?
>> This map was made in 1823, but by 1848,
it was pretty much plowed over and not
visible from the ground anymore.
>> So, it's been basically destroyed.
>> Right. Uh so, it was a huge structure.
This is only 13 acres here, and this is
100 acres.
>> Wow, almost 10 times bigger.
>> We know that Thomas Jefferson was
actually very interested in this
particular earthwork. It goes back to
1803, even when he was president. He
asked a general to draw these very same
earthworks.
>> The reason for Jefferson's interest, the
Louisiana Purchase.
The US bought Louisiana from the French.
They had taken it from the Spanish.
Jefferson wanted to prove others were
here in America earlier, so Spain
couldn't say Louisiana or any other land
belonged to them.
I recently investigated the notion that
Lewis and Clark were assigned to look
for evidence of Welsh contact. I looked
at the Brandenburg Stone as one
possibility that that may have been
carved by the Welsh.
>> He was also interested in the
possibility of the lost tribes of
Israel, so he even asked Lewis and Clark
to look for them, so
he was covering all the bases. Roman or
Greek or Phoenician, he would have been
just as happy or
to to to prove it wasn't the Spanish. I
think there was a diplomatic interest
there.
>> I'll bet you in his back pocket he had
this right here.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, an earthwork like this, I
mean, to me this just screams an early
Jewish culture, but there's something
more that's significant here. This is a
massive mound. This isn't something done
by one or two or a few people. This
involved a lot of people, right?
>> This earthworks
uh would have required a whole community
years to build.
The whole community was dedicated to
building
this particular symbol, and therefore
it's a much deeper involvement with the
indigenous culture than the other
artifacts.
>> I would agree with you. I think
collectively though they're all
important.
It seems clear to me that these
artifacts don't have anything to do with
the lost tribes.
Others maybe, but not these.
So it begs the question,
if the lost tribes didn't create these
artifacts, who did?
By studying the Bat Creek Stone, a
mysterious artifact found in a Tennessee
burial mound more than 100 years ago, I
confirmed that its inscription is much
older than its discovery date.
It's carved with a message for the
Judeans. Judea is a region in Israel and
the writing style is consistent with
Jews after the turn of the 1st century.
Could a group of them have been here in
America at that time?
That would rule out my initial theory,
the lost tribes of Israel, who went
missing from history much earlier. But I
think there's a chance the lost tribes'
descendants might be responsible. I'm
going to meet a local rabbi.
If I can learn more about the history of
Jewish people coming to America, it
could help me solve the mystery of the
Bat Creek Stone and the menorah-shaped
mounds I just learned about.
Rabbi, how you doing?
I'm investigating ancient Hebrews here
in the United States and I want to try
to figure out who's responsible. But I
want to know a little bit more about
early Jews coming to America. What do
you know about that?
>> So, what we do know is that Columbus
came in 1492 and with him he brought
Jews. And the first question that begs
is, well, why on earth would he do that?
And he believed at the time that there
were potentially in the New World these
lost tribes. He would want people who he
thought
could communicate with them.
>> Well, that's interesting that Jews
traveled with Columbus. Aren't there
some rumors that people thought that
maybe he was Jewish himself?
>> There's a big controversy and I'll leave
this to historians to resolve that. But
even if he wasn't Jewish, he certainly
had Jewish companions, understood the
Jewish community, and was keen on
discovering the the lost tribes.
>> There was a lot of persecution going on,
wasn't there?
>> Up until 1492, we we talk about
historically as the golden age of Spain
for the Jews, and things had been going
there pretty well. Jews were relatively
left alone to thrive in business and
religious tradition and what have you,
and then we get this edict in 1492, and
people were left with just a horrible
choice, either die by the sword or
convert.
>> Though 1492 is best known as the year
Columbus sailed the ocean blue,
it was also an infamous year for the
persecution of Jewish people.
There was the burning at the stake of 24
Jews in Germany, and the expulsion of
100,000 in Sicily.
The worst persecution,
the Edict of Expulsion in Spain, which
gave Jews 4 months to leave Spain,
convert to Catholicism, or face death.
>> The rabbis, some said better to survive,
um even if you have to convert to
Catholicism, your life is more
important, and others said no, it's
better to be a martyr and to die than to
ever worship in ways that are are
inauthentic and you don't believe. Tens
of thousands of them died.
But we also know that thousands of them
converted to Catholicism and still
maintained their religious Jewish
traditions at home. We call those people
who were forced to convert conversos.
>> So they were secretly Jewish, but they
were outwardly Catholic.
>> These conversos, or what are sometimes
also called crypto Jews, were practicing
Catholicism, but practicing their
Judaism in the closet. Everything from
lighting candles in private on Friday
nights to refraining from eating pork
and following the kosher laws. So these
conversos really tried to maintain some
sense of their their Jewish identity and
they carried that to the New World with
them.
>> We know that many of the conversos, the
crypto-Jews, made their way to the
northern frontier of Mexico in what is
now New Mexico and and the American
Southwest.
>> It makes perfect sense. I mean, this is
something that many people have done,
many religions have done, is come to the
Americas to practice freedom of
religion.
>> Even today, there continue to be many
Latino families who are outwardly
practicing Catholicism or Christianity,
but who privately continue to observe
some of these Jewish rituals that have
been passed down to them over time.
>> Well, in this case you're talking about
modern-day people that are practicing
rituals that date back possibly as far
as the 15th century. I've been looking
at artifacts that go back much further.
One example is the Bat Creek Stone and
the language is early Semitic script
that some scholars say dates back to the
first century.
So, I'm really interested in trying to
get to the bottom of this and find
anything I can that might be related. Is
there anything that you know of that
could possibly be related to to what
could be ancient Jewish writing?
>> I can't claim to the veracity of this,
but there is a woman in New Mexico who
claimed to have found this on her
father's property and there are some
historians who believe that this
evidence is
early, potentially Semitic or Hebrew
writing. Perhaps there's something
there.
>> What the rabbi is showing me isn't the
only carving with the Hebrew connection
in New Mexico.
There's another one called the Los Lunas
Decalogue Stone and the Ten Commandments
are carved on it in Paleo-Hebrew.
Maybe there's a connection between that
boulder and the petroglyph pictures
which the rabbi is showing me.
The thing that's really jumping out is
it looks weathered. If this is down in
New Mexico and there's any possibility
that this could be old Hebrew or old
Jewish writing, I'm going to have to
check this out.
In my investigation, there's one thing I
know for certain. Much of what we think
we know about our history is wrong.
We know Jewish people came to America
with Columbus.
And the Bat Creek stone proves they came
here in the first century, too.
But there may be others. Perhaps the
lost tribes who came here even earlier.
And the people I'm about to meet may
have found proof.
Are you Stacy?
>> I am. This is my friend Ron.
>> I've got Ron here.
I'm investigating the likelihood that
there were ancient Hebrew tribes, people
that came here from across the Atlantic
going back at least hundreds of years,
perhaps thousands. I recently talked to
a rabbi friend of mine back in
Minneapolis who said there were Hebrew
carvings down here. Tell me about them.
>> We have found several on my dad's land
up here and Ron found many of these all
around New Mexico. All of these drawings
that we're anxious for you to look at.
>> Well, I've got these pictures from a
friend of mine Jimmy's ranch. So, what
are these?
>> They're ligatures. That's written in a
script form that makes it easier for
people that know the language and people
that don't to understand in a in a
picture.
>> I mean, the earliest communication that
humans had was through pictures. Maybe
that's what we have going on here. These
look fascinating.
Maybe we should go take a look at them.
What do you say?
>> Yeah.
>> Let's go. If you have a four-wheel
drive, it's pretty rough and remote out
there. I got a couple.
>> Mhm.
>> Let's go.
>> All right. Okay.
>> I'm in New Mexico looking for ligatures.
They're symbols that take on new meaning
when they're combined.
They could be evidence that Jews came to
America long before Columbus.
Maybe they were clues left by members of
the legendary lost tribes of Israel.
Jewish tribes that went missing in 722
BC.
I'm heading to the discovery site to see
for myself.
So, Ronnie, you have to tell me, how did
you find these things?
>> I was building these roads through here
and
got out of the bulldozer and and ran
across this rock.
>> Saw this over here on the side of rocks.
>> This is not the first time I've seen
evidence here in in North America of
early Hebrews coming here. I mean, I've
looked at the Decalogue Stone, the Bat
Creek Stone, the Tucson Lead Artifacts,
and the Hanaki Earthworks absolutely
suggest that there were early Jews here
in America
long before Columbus, and we certainly
weren't taught that in school, were we?
>> No, no.
Uh here we are.
Wow, what do you think of that?
Well, Ron, not only is it rugged out
here, but it's remote. I mean,
why would somebody come out here to
carve a hoax or graffiti? I mean, nobody
would see it.
This whole panel is full of carvings.
And up there, too.
It would be easy to assume these are
Native American petroglyphs, but I don't
think they are.
I've never seen anything quite like this
before. You see this dark surface on
this rock? This developed over at least
hundreds of years, probably thousands of
years.
You can actually see where some of the
edges have spalled. You see how it's
almost white, sort of a tan color? Well,
that's what these would have looked like
when they were first made. But, they're
dark. They're almost black, like the
background rock that they're carved
into. This is definitely not modern.
This is my handheld portable microscope.
And you can see how dark that is.
You know, another thing that jumps out
at me right away
that I'm sure you guys have noticed,
that they didn't take a hammer and
chisel. This was carved with rocks, and
they used the pecking technique. Can you
see that? Mhm.
It's like it's pitted. I saw something
on the way in that could help us put a
date on these carvings.
It's the sort of thing many people frown
upon, but as a geologist, I can find
some value in it. It's graffiti.
Let's go take a look at this other site.
>> Aha.
That's what I wanted to show you.
You can see that this is fresh looking.
It's carved into the same dark surface.
This one's dated 1892. It looks like it
was carved yesterday.
>> Mhm.
>> Some other carvings here, 1925, 1924,
1919.
>> Mhm.
>> And they all look fresh.
I mean, this is just a quick and dirty
comparison, but you can see this looks a
lot different than what we have back
there. It's pretty dramatic, isn't it?
It's definitely older than 120 years,
easily hundreds of years old. Who knows
how far back. So, at this point it
becomes important to talk to the experts
in this script. And my question is, do
we know what this script is?
>> Right. Well, we did reach out to a few
experts and they dated it to the 15th
century BC.
>> 15th century BC?
>> BC.
>> That's 3,500 years ago.
>> It's a script that predates the Hebrew
alphabet.
>> Okay, what's it called?
>> It's called Old Negev.
>> Old Negev is an ancient script.
Experts believe it was developed by
ancestors of the biblical Abraham who
worked in the Egyptian mines in West
Central Sinai.
The laborers needed a way to express
their language in writing.
Some consider Old Negev to be a
precursor to Phoenician, Paleo-Hebrew,
and early Arabic scripts.
The name Negev came up when I examined
the Bat Creek stone in Tennessee. Its
inscription reads, "For the Judeans."
The Judeans lived in what's now the
northern Negev desert.
>> The people we reached out to gave us uh
some rough translations of this.
>> So, it's read right to left?
>> It's yeah, from from right to left. So,
we're talking in this area here, "Woe
and sorrow."
Uh on this inscription in here.
>> Okay.
>> Then we move over here to this and this
would be to cover or veil.
This one right down here would be
sunburnt or black.
And it's talking about uh brothers and
relatives, fellow man and friend to cry
out or call for help.
>> Talking about woe and sorrow and
sunburnt, there is a rock shelter here.
It would provide protection from the
sun.
>> Right.
>> So, maybe this is where they took refuge
during a long journey and took the time
to carve this.
>> Mhm.
>> And we're talking old Negev script.
That's 3,500 years ago.
The weathering of this inscription could
certainly be that old.
My gosh, that's 700 years before the
lost tribes. Well, we don't know if this
is that old, but if it is that old,
I mean, that would be amazing, wouldn't
it?
>> It would.
That is so interesting that you say the
lost tribes because there is one figure
on here that a friend of mine who lived
in Israel for several years said is
associated with the tribe of Judah.
>> This isn't the first time in this
investigation that the name Judah has
come up.
The Bat Creek stone inscription reads,
"For the Judeans." in Paleo-Hebrew.
Judea is a region named after the tribe
of Judah.
The tribe of Judah, that's Jesus' tribe.
>> Right.
>> And if this is indeed 3,500 years old,
that would be 1,500 years before Jesus.
>> Or oh.
>> So, this would have been his distant
ancestors that could have used this
script. But the other possibility is
that this could have been a group that
came later. We don't know. Sometimes
people will use outdated languages far
into the future. I mean the the
Catholics still use Latin during mass
and in our culture today Latin is
essentially a dead language. So
the lost tribes being responsible for
this I guess is still on the table.
Whoever this group is traveled far and
wide it sounds like. There's going to be
archaeologists that are going to watch
this and they're going to scoff. When
what they should be doing is respecting
the work that we're trying to do here.
The argument that the oceans were these
vast impenetrable barriers to me is
ridiculous. Here yet another group
probably did come over here in the
distant past.
The Bat Creek stone is physically small
compared to a lot of things I
investigate.
But there's a big mystery attached to
it.
After studying the Bat Creek stone with
my 3D microscope and meeting with
someone else who studied it, I'm
convinced it's not a hoax.
I think it was left in America by a 1st
century Jewish group. But I can't say
for sure who they were or why they left
it.
I no longer think the lost tribes were
involved. The timing's just not right.
But the Bat Creek stone does connect
early Jews with pre-Columbian America.
Decalogue stones with the 10
Commandments,
earthwork shaped like a menorah,
and strange petroglyphs in the Southwest
also point to unexpected Jewish visitors
to the New World.
Whatever happened to the lost tribes of
Israel when they disappeared in 722 BC
is still a mystery. But it's one I hope
to solve someday.
>> Cuz my main interest at the time was
exploring the cave.
I wanted to know what it was, how far it
went.
There are bronze weapons in there,
swords, spears, shields, knives, many
artifacts, something like 7,000. No two
are exactly the same.
It proves that many of the things that
have been taught elementary school, high
school, and college is
is wrong.
They were treasure hunters searching for
that cave. So, I have decided to
completely hide its location.
Search all you want, you will never find
it.
>> The history that we were all taught
growing up is wrong.
My name is Scott Wolter, and I'm a
forensic geologist.
There's a hidden history that that
nobody knows about.
There are pyramids, chambers, tombs,
descriptions. They're all over the
world.
We're going to investigate these
artifacts and sites, and we're going to
get to the truth.
Sometimes history isn't what we've been
told.
>> Our country is filled with caves,
caverns, and burial chambers that could
hide artifacts and sacred wonders from
long ago.
I've looked for the Ark of the Covenant,
the Holy Grail, and other things rumored
to be hidden here.
I think these things are just waiting to
be found by those who search hard
enough.
Without a doubt, some of the greatest
lost treasures of all time are those
from ancient Egypt, where vast burial
chambers lie virtually empty,
the Pharaoh's riches having vanished.
Many people believe these old-world
artifacts were brought to the New World,
and I think they could be right.
A few years ago, I examined some alleged
Egyptian artifacts said to have been
found in a cave in rural Illinois.
But Illinois isn't the only place said
to hide such treasures.
That's why I'm heading to another place
where many think ancient Egyptians once
came with their vast riches,
the Grand Canyon.
Stretching 277
mi, the Grand Canyon is about 18 mi wide
and up to 6,000 ft deep.
It was carved out by the Colorado River
about 500 million years ago, and the
layering of the rock reveals a huge
amount of our nation's geological
history.
And there are caves here, but only a few
of them have been explored.
So, if ancient Egyptians brought their
treasure here, it's likely still hidden,
and I'm meeting a guy who says he knows
where it is.
Well, Jerry, thanks for meeting me here
today in this amazing place.
>> It is. It's very amazing.
>> You know, there are many myths and
stories about ancient cultures coming to
America with fantastic treasures. Some
people say that there's a treasure
buried here somewhere in the Grand
Canyon. And I have a newspaper article
from the Phoenix Gazette 1909 that talks
about a treasure here.
Let's take a look at this.
Explorations in Grand Canyon, mysteries
of immense rich cavern being brought to
light.
Remarkable finds indicate ancient people
migrated from the Orient. And that's
amazing.
>> Yeah, it is. And you know, the person
who did this exploration was G.E.
Kinkaid. He'd been hired by the
Smithsonian and he went pretty much
looking for this cave full of treasure
and this lost city that's down there.
>> Did he find it? And what happened after
that?
>> Kinkaid knew what he was looking for. He
pretty much went to the spot,
found a series of steps that went up the
cliff wall,
went into the cave. He found not only
hieroglyphs, but he found all kinds of
artifacts.
>> Like what?
>> Well, there was statuary, there were
mummies in there, there were indeed
pieces of
gold and silver.
>> Now, one of the things they mention here
is that this particular cave is
virtually inaccessible. Although it does
talk about 1,400, 1,500 steps, sandstone
steps that were carved into the rock
that would allow them to to get there.
The other thing that's amazing to me is,
according to the article, this cave is
so massive that 50,000 people could have
lived there. So, potentially there could
have been
thousands, if not millions, of artifacts
inside this cave and the fact that we
look around here and we see this
geology, we know we've got sandstone,
limestone. It's going to lend itself to
caves and I know that there's a lot of
caves here. So, you know, that fits.
But today the Smithsonian's official
position is that this whole story is a
hoax. Is that correct?
>> We contacted the Smithsonian.
They deny that there's a cave, that
there's any evidence, that there was
anything here.
>> So, are you suggesting that the
Smithsonian is covering up something
here in the Grand Canyon?
>> Oh, they absolutely are.
>> As I know that you've done a lot of work
out here. You've made some expeditions
here. What did you find?
>> Well, we came here trying to find the
truth. Kathy, my wife, did the research
over a number of years and finally
pinpointed a spot that we believe is
exactly where this would need to be if
it truly existed.
>> So, where is that location?
>> You know, this is a really difficult
place to get to, Scott. It isn't easy at
all. But yeah, I can show you where we
believe the cave is at.
>> So, you're up for it?
>> I'd be happy to show you what we know.
>> But Jerry, what makes you so sure that
you know where this site is?
>> Well, once we got to the site that Kathy
had identified, we started looking very
closely at anything that might have been
left behind by the Smithsonian explorers
and excavation team that had been there
ahead of us.
We found buttons, pieces of glassware, a
name badge,
uh several small pieces that were 80 to
100 years old.
>> So, do you think this corresponds with
the expedition back in 1909?
>> Yeah, I do. Uh this this place is very
dangerous.
>> Why do you say that?
>> Well, it's dangerous because while we
were there on several occasions, there
were government stealth helicopters.
>> Stealth helicopters? Seriously?
>> They know what's there, Scott, and we
know that they know what's there.
>> So, you think they were trying to scare
you off?
>> I know they were trying to scare us off.
>> Let me tell you this, if there's an
ancient site somewhere down in the Grand
Canyon, possibly Egyptian, they're not
going to scare me off.
Ancient Egypt is famous for its vast
riches and immense wealth.
When King Tut's tomb was discovered in
1922,
his coffin alone was made from solid
gold and was worth over $13 million.
Much
Much of the treasure attributed to
Egyptian pharaohs has yet to be found.
So, what I want to know is, could it be
here in America?
If it was hidden away on US soil, some
people think it's in the Grand Canyon.
An old news article suggests Egyptian
treasure was found here.
And another treasure might be here, too.
The Ark of the Covenant.
My search for the religious relic turned
up clues nearby in Arizona's Petrified
Forest National Park.
If any treasure is here in the canyon,
it's in an incredibly dangerous and
inaccessible spot, possibly even guarded
by the government. But, the reward is
too great, and I have to find out what's
hidden here.
>> There were things that were going on
that just didn't make any sense for such
a remote location.
>> I want to find this thing wherever it
is, and I need your help.
>> This area where the cave is located is
considered sacred ground by the Hopi,
Navajo, Zuni, and other tribes of this
area.
>> Do you think that maybe they might have
some information that could be helpful
to us?
>> Well, I know someone who might have some
answers to fill in the blanks.
>> The Zuni tribe are Pueblo people who
have made the Southwest their home for
hundreds of years.
To the Zuni, the Grand Canyon is a holy
place. Their creation story telling how
the ancestors climbed up from its basin.
Even today, Zuni men still make
pilgrimages to the Grand Canyon to
venerate this sacred site. Clifford, as
a Zuni tribal elder, what can you tell
me about the Grand Canyon and what it
means to your people?
>> Well, the Grand Canyon to the Zuni
people and other Pueblo tribes, this is
considered our
place of origin, not only in terms of
religion, but also of spirituality about
where our forefathers and our ancient
ones came out of.
>> Is there anything in your creation
stories
that talks about some of these
mysterious caves, maybe even the one
that could possibly hold Egyptian
artifacts?
>> In our spiritual teachings, there are
actually rooms inside the Grand Canyon
and there's several passageways.
>> Right.
>> So, that parallels with some of the
history about the early 1900s and also
about some of the the treasures that a
lot of Indian tribes talked about.
>> Are there any stories about what might
be in some of these caves?
>> Uh I've heard a lot of different stories
from different tribes that
talk about these treasures that are
supposedly in there.
But then also I heard about a pyramid
that's supposedly inside the Grand
Canyon.
>> A pyramid?
>> A pyramid.
>> So, Clifford, your oral stories say that
there were cities inside of these caves
and pyramids in the Grand Canyon.
>> I absolutely believe in that because
there's been a lot of different crosses
of different cultures. This part of the
world is my understanding that there was
a lot of Egyptian type
relics and
artifacts that were taken from the
inside the Grand Canyon.
>> Are there any stories about any of these
caves being cursed?
>> In most Native American sites, they're
natural occurrences that might be
considered cursed. It's sort of like a
guardian type thing and it's still even
in existence to this day.
>> You got to have to tread very carefully.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, do you think there still could be
treasure down there?
>> Oh, absolutely. This is a huge place.
And if you look at the rooms and the the
space inside the canyon itself,
there's a lot of artifacts of past
civilizations.
I believe in that that there's a lot of
treasure still inside the canyon.
>> Do you think we can get there?
>> Well, you might try getting there, but
it's very dangerous.
>> Well, you know, I appreciate what uh
Clifford was saying, but I'm not ready
to give up yet.
We have to figure out a way to get into
the old cave.
>> Well, it's a very dangerous place.
Clifford was right. Well, I have some
video to show you of our 2002 expedition
into the canyon. It'll show you exactly
how dangerous a place this is.
>> Sounds good. Let's take a look.
>> This is our camp from our 2002
expedition when we were at the Grand
Canyon trying to find a way down to the
area where Kinkaid's cave would be
found.
>> It looks like it drops straight off,
right?
>> Beyond this point is just a sheer 2,000
ft drop-off. People standing here on the
edge of the canyon
past that point, it is straight down
maybe 2,000 ft.
>> Just what I'm seeing here does look
I mean, that's that's a pretty steep
slope.
>> It it's absolutely dangerous. Absolutely
dangerous. And here you see now they've
gone over the edge, they're hanging off
the ropes. They've gone down maybe 800
ft.
And and this one fellow's just hanging
off the rope. They're suffering heat
exhaustion. There's no way you can carry
enough water to get to this place.
>> So basically what you're saying is to
get to this cave
I mean, it's virtually impossible.
>> It is.
All right, what you're looking at here
is while our team was going down
descending into the canyon over these
cliffs
you can see very clearly
>> Holy crap.
>> there's this unmarked plane that's
flying well below the canyon
rim. As you see it going right through
there.
We've also seen helicopters and they've
buzzed us at various times we've been
there. They don't they don't have any
markings either. And we feel they must
be
government helicopters, government
airplanes. They were watching us.
>> Or maybe they were trying to scare you
off.
>> Probably trying to.
>> So they never did get down to the cave
entrance.
>> They never did. Yeah, it proved to be
way too difficult. Heat exhaustion took
over and it was really very difficult to
get them back to the surface.
>> Do you think that we could climb down
here realistically?
>> No.
>> how long would that take? What are we
talking about time-wise?
>> You need expert mountaineers and a lot
of rope.
>> Well, you know what?
There might be another way to get there.
>> All right. What do you have in mind?
>> Here we are over the Colorado River. I
need you to tell me exactly where you
need me to go.
>> Yeah, it's just right down there below
that ridge.
>> So, I'm going to do an orbit. I'm going
to lose a little bit of altitude here
and do an orbit over the location.
>> Right there. We need to descend down
below that ridgeline in order to see
directly across into the canyon.
>> I can't do that. The FAA has restricted
all flight below the canyon rim. Not
allowed to descend down there.
>> So, you're telling me that the FAA, the
government, will not allow us to go down
there?
>> Absolutely not.
>> Copter 49er 174
>> We need to descend down below that ridge
line in order to see directly across.
>> The FAA has restricted all flight below
the canyon rim. Not allowed to descend
down there.
>> So you're saying that the government
will not allow us to fly over this area
right here? This is where the the
Egyptian cave is supposed to be?
>> No sir, we're not allowed down there.
>> That's the level that we think that the
cave is at. Right there.
>> Okay. Just beyond that next drop off.
>> That next?
>> Exactly.
>> So Jerry, we are pretty much above it on
top of it, you think?
>> Yeah, there's the circle of rocks from
our campsite.
>> Is there any way that we could get down
on that plateau just above it? Could you
Could you land there?
>> We can land on the top. I can get you on
that plateau right over there.
>> Okay. Well, that would I guess that's
the next best thing.
>> Roger. Can I go ahead and land right
down there?
>> Okay. 69er
>> 10 9780 49er is landing. I'll call you
back at the mirror.
>> So Jerry, this was your base camp right
here, right? This is where you started
your operation to get down to what you
hoped was the Egyptian cave?
>> This is it.
Well, we were here before. The guys that
were going over, we thought they were
prepared. We really didn't know what it
would take at the time. And they went
down about 800 ft and they ended up
getting stuck.
>> 800 ft, that's only about what, halfway
down to where you think the cave is?
>> It's about halfway, yeah.
Going over the side,
it just seems impossible. You can't see
the cave from the bottom. Nor can you
see it from the top. It's at an
in-between level, it's completely
obscured.
>> That newspaper article is very
compelling from 1909. Something happened
here in the Grand Canyon. I think the
government is hiding something. The fact
that a plane flew by when you guys were
down here rappelling tells me that they
had to have been watching you. They're
guarding something. The oral stories of
the Zuni and other tribes around the
Grand Canyon clearly suggest that some
people came here, that there are many
caves here, but there may be caves that
housed ancient cultures and maybe
artifacts, possibly the Egyptians. So
I'm convinced that there is something
here.
>> Well, we've only scratched the surface
and we're sure that there were ancient
cultures who came through here. It could
have been the Egyptians. We think it was
someone from the Orient. There's some
talk that even the Ark of the Covenant
might have come through here.
>> You know, I recently was in the
Petrified Forest and I saw a petroglyph
that looked just like the Ark of the
Covenant. So maybe the Ark of the
Covenant did come to North America
through the Petrified Forest. Maybe it's
down there in that cave.
After taking a a look around, it's clear
that further exploration is impossible.
It frustrates me not to reach this cave,
but it isn't the only cave in America
rumored to hide Egyptian treasure.
There's another cave in southern
Illinois,
and while I've studied artifacts
allegedly taken from it, I've never seen
the cave itself.
I met the man who claims he found this
cave, Russell Burrows, and I even got
his story on camera.
>> There were people searching for that
cave, treasure hunters.
So, I had decided that the best thing to
do
is to completely hide its location,
which I did.
>> Now, he won't talk to me at all.
But maybe it's time to go look for the
cave and see once and for all if Russell
was telling the truth.
You know, speaking of treasures, there's
another cave in southern Illinois,
Burrows Cave, I'm sure you've heard of
it.
>> We have.
>> I've actually spent quite a bit of time
looking at the artifacts, but I've never
found the cave, and that's where I'm
headed next. I want to find Burrows
Cave.
If I can find Burrows Cave, it would be
a huge step toward proving Egyptian
treasure really did make it to America.
And that's why I need to visit someone
who may know just how to find it, Harry
Hubbard, an artifact collector and
researcher who's devoted his life to
study the Illinois treasure cave.
Harry has some examples of the treasures
that he's eager for me to see.
This is amazing. It looks like the
greatest hoard of treasure I've ever
seen in person.
But they're not gold. These are made of
lead, right?
>> That's correct. These are replicas of
original gold pieces brought out in
1985.
>> What happened all the gold? Where is it?
These are replicas.
>> Right. Well, Burrows melted the gold and
then sold it off.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
You know, I'm seeing Egyptian
iconography. I'm seeing some interesting
text, a sun god symbol. To see all this
stuff that you have here and to think
that it was actual gold treasure at one
time is amazing. I mean, it's got to be
one of the greatest hoards in history.
>> The original pieces came from here in
Marion County. There's an ancient tomb
very nearby.
>> Okay, the cave, right?
>> All right. Tell me about the cave.
>> The original description indicated that
there were 13 crypts.
>> Okay.
>> The main crypt had a king in a solid
gold sarcophagus. And there was one
crypt that actually had a woman in it.
And the rest were ancient kings. 13
cadavers buried in one crypt.
>> So, you're convinced that that the gold
that came out was real?
>> Oh, yes. Most definitely.
>> Well, let's get back to Russell Burrows.
He's the guy that told me fantastic
stories about pulling out not just gold
artifacts, but
artifacts carved and made out of stone.
I've talked to him about these
artifacts.
>> And did you study those artifacts?
>> Absolutely, I did.
>> What did you determine?
>> Well, I can tell you with absolute
certainty that I think I know what's
behind this notorious mystery of the
Illinois cave and how it might connect
with the Grand Canyon cave that I just
looked at.
>> I'm on the hunt for Egyptian treasure
that legend say is buried somewhere in
America.
The big question is, where is it?
I've checked out a prohibited area at
the Grand Canyon in Arizona.
And now I'm examining replicas of
possible Egyptian artifacts found in
another cavernous hiding place here in
southern Illinois.
Legend says the original gold and the
other carved pieces were taken from a
cave here in the 1980s.
But whether this is a true story or a
tall tale remains to be seen.
I've spent years trying to get to the
truth myself.
In 2010, I managed to get the only
interview of Russell Burrows ever known
to be filmed and I examined some of the
artifacts he claimed he found.
The varied collection ranged from a
shaman and a cartouche carved in black
marble to a white marble stone with the
Greek goddess Isis on it.
But after I questioned their
authenticity, Russell refused to speak
with me again.
>> The key to the mysterious cave in
Illinois here really centers on Russell
Burrows. I mean, he's the one that made
the cave famous. That's why they call it
Burrows Cave.
>> Uh he is the reason that a lot of people
have become skeptical of the artifacts
because a lot of them have been tainted
and forged.
>> You know, I felt it was important to
give Russell an opportunity to say
something about it. So I interviewed him
back in 2010.
>> I'd like to see what he's got to say.
>> Well, 1982,
uh I was
uh out working with my metal detector
searching for an old homestead.
I was walking down the the trail on the
bluff and I stepped on a rock which
dropped me into a pit or a hole.
And lo and behold behind it was a cave.
There are bronze weapons in there,
swords, spears, shields, knives, many
artifacts, many many something like
7,000. No two are exactly the same.
>> Well, that's quite a story, isn't it?
>> This one is different from the rest of
them.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yes. The story changes quite frequently.
>> Well, one of the things that does jump
out at me is his
descriptions of what he sees in the cave
are incredibly detailed.
>> Well, Burrows describes 13 crypts. The
main crypt is a man in the solid gold
sarcophagus.
>> Do you think
>> I believe he saw those things.
>> Well, I have an artifact I want to show
you.
That's the Isis Stone.
Uh an Egyptian-looking female who's
kneeling in reverence to
Ra, the sun god.
And
this is an artifact that uh if you look
closer um is very revealing.
You look right here.
You can see that there are some carved
characters here. This is English cursive
writing.
>> Mhm.
>> Why would English writing be on an
ancient Egyptian artifact? That's
problem number one. This particular
stone is exactly 2 in thick. As are most
modern white marble tombstones used
between about 1850 and 1950. Very
commonly used at that time. But it gets
more interesting after that. If you look
at this kind of dark gray material,
>> Mhm.
>> that's actually modern mortar.
>> Okay.
>> The next thing that happened here is you
see these chips on the backside.
>> Right.
>> Somebody chipped the backside apparently
to try to remove the inscriptions on the
back and make it look old. So, there's
no question in my mind that this is a
fake artifact and that it was made from
a modern white marble tombstone.
But, that doesn't mean that the cave
doesn't exist. In fact, it could very
well exist and I have a couple of
artifacts that I want to show you that
Russell claims came from
his cave.
It looks like uh perhaps it's an
Egyptian shaman. It's got the Egyptian
beard. It has a very creepy look to it
and it could very well be authentic. Who
knows?
This is another artifact that looks very
interesting to me. This is a cartouche,
an Egyptian cartouche, and in most cases
a cartouche has carried the names
of a pharaoh or somebody of importance.
>> Well, these two are are authentic.
There's no doubt in my mind. There's not
that many people that know Egyptian
glyph and the ones that are carved in
Egyptian glyph, the grammar, syntax,
everything is pretty much correct.
>> After looking at all these artifacts
here, looking at all the replicas of the
gold, imagining this vast treasure
underground,
my question to you is, do you think the
cave is real?
>> I know the cave is real and we know how
all this came over here.
Come on, let me show you something.
>> Okay.
>> This is the man who brought all the
treasures over here from Egypt.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yes.
>> And who is this?
>> His name is Alexander Helios.
He is the missing son of Cleopatra and
Mark Antony.
>> Alexander Helios was an Egyptian prince
whose famous parents, Antony and
Cleopatra, committed suicide when a
Roman emperor conquered Egypt.
Alexander Helios, as the eldest son, may
have feared for his life and fled the
country with the family fortune.
At the time, Egypt had many sailing
ships. So, perhaps Helios came to what's
now America to seek refuge, bringing his
treasure with him.
All right. So, why did he come over
here?
>> One of the stones clearly says we left
the Mediterranean
to escape persecution. And he's all over
these artifacts, probably on about 500
of them. And it tells his life story
here. After about age 10, he vanishes
off of the face of history.
>> Okay.
>> But here we have him as an older man, as
a younger man, in different uh costumes.
He was a priest of the sun, and that was
his name, Helios, which which is Greek
for the sun.
>> Oh, okay. So, you think he came here?
>> Yes.
>> And when was this?
>> Probably about 25 BC.
>> Well, that's very interesting. And how
many people do you think came with him?
>> According to the tablets, probably
50,000.
>> 50,000 people. Well, that's pretty
interesting because when I was out at
the uh cave in the Grand Canyon, they
talked about it being big enough to
house 50,000 people. And maybe
the cave that you have here, that you
think is here, maybe those people also
went out to the Grand Canyon.
>> So, what do you think of the theory that
Alexander Helios came here to North
America with all these treasures?
>> Well, it's interesting for a couple
reasons. One is Helios and the people
you talk about are real historic
figures. And the fact is they did
disappear from the pages of history. And
they had to go somewhere. Why not here?
So, I like it from that standpoint, but
I need to see more evidence before I'm
convinced. I mean, these are great, but
I need to find that cave. Do you know
where that cave is?
>> Yes, we know where the cave is.
>> All right, show me.
>> Now, this map
came from the file cabinet of one of
Russell Burrows' associates. I've been
researching this for 20 years.
And
there's been a few things that I was
wrong about here and there, but the
location of this tomb is not one of
them.
>> Okay.
>> This is what we call the pinpoint map.
>> All right. So, this is his secret map,
right?
>> This is Russell Burrows' this secret
map.
And if you'll notice, there's a ravine
system here.
And right here, there's dots
right here, and also there's a red dot
right here.
>> Okay.
>> There's a cavern in one ravine and a
large room underneath the ground of the
other one.
>> Okay.
>> And I'm going to put an X right there
and right there.
>> So, X marks the spot.
>> You got it.
>> How far away is this uh ravine system?
>> About 4 and 1/2 miles away.
>> Well, Harry, if you're right, I've got
to get out there and find this cave.
You know, there's always truth in
legend. We have to get to the truth, and
that's what I'm going to find.
Some people believe that ancient
Egyptians may have come to America with
their treasure.
And now, I'm searching for these caves
that may hide these amazing artifacts.
I visited the Grand Canyon, where it's
believed there were caverns of vast
riches from afar.
And here in Illinois, I've examined
replicas of the many Egyptian artifacts
that are said to have come from Burrows'
Cave.
>> When I saw them, I said to myself,
"Where in the world did these come?"
>> Using the secret treasure map that Harry
Hubbard gave me, I've tracked down the
landowner of the area on the map.
And although Harry wasn't allowed on the
site, I've been given access. And if
there's a cave here, I'm going to find
it.
I'm investigating the possibility of
Egyptians bringing treasure to America.
I was just out in the Grand Canyon and I
investigated a mysterious cave that is
alleged to contain treasures. And now
I'm here in southern Illinois
investigating the Burrows Cave mystery,
another Egyptian treasure
possibility here. What do you think
about all this?
>> I think it's a very fantastic legend.
How could people from the Middle East
have made it across the Atlantic up the
Mississippi and have found this spot
here out in the middle of nowhere?
>> I can appreciate your skepticism, but
there is an historical figure called
Alexander Helios who about 2,000 years
ago did disappear from the pages of
history. And he was of Egyptian
heritage, he did have ships, he did have
a following, and the question is where
did he go? The other thing that is
really interesting and compelling to me
is that there are at least 7,000
artifacts that reportedly did come from
Burrows Cave. I've seen a couple
thousand of them myself, and some of
them are quite ornate and beautiful, and
they had to come from somewhere. Those
are two things that do intrigue me, but
I want to hear more about what you have
here. And this is supposed to be the
area where the cave is. What do you know
about it?
>> I'll let me show you on my aerial view
here of my property here.
>> Okay.
>> We have the road to the north that we
entered here, and we're parked right
here at the edge of the the woods and
this open field.
And there's supposedly two ravines where
these Egyptian tombs or caverns are are
supposed to be located.
>> Okay. I do have a map here that I'd like
to compare with your map.
Okay.
So, here is your It looks like it's
right here. So, that would put us These
are the two ravines you're talking about
right here?
>> Correct.
>> So, apparently
this is where Burrows Cave is is
located.
>> That's what most people believe, yes.
>> Are you willing to take me in there?
>> Yes, I am, Scott.
>> Discovering Burrows Cave here in
Illinois would be the find of the
century.
But, the question surrounding the
veracity of the artifacts discovery are
a problem for most everyone, including
me.
I want to know, did Russell Burrows
really find and conceal this cave, or
did it ever exist at all?
His own account suggests it's off a
trail near some bluffs, just like the
bluffs on Steven's land. So, I think
we're in the right area.
Burrows said he slipped into a pit that
led him into a long treasure cave.
My examination of the geology here will
be key.
If there's not a cave here, then I need
to analyze the rock to see if there
could be one underground.
>> Well, Scott, this is the west ravine.
>> That is a natural rock shelter.
Does it go under here, too?
>> Yes, there's a ledge underneath where
we're standing.
>> Pretty impressive, actually.
Can we get down there? I sure would like
to look around here a little more.
>> Yeah, there's a trail over here to our
right that leads down into the
ravine.
>> The first thing I can say is the rock
shelter in the ravine is not a cave, but
a cave entrance discovered back in 1982
might have become hidden by a rockfall,
or overgrown by trees in the 30 years
since Burrows first found it.
>> I'm not ready to give up on the idea
ancient Egyptians might have come here
and tunneled out deep into rock.
But to find out if that's possible, I'll
need to test the rock type.
>> So Scott, here we're at the spot that
was marked as an X on your map, but I
don't see any caverns or
uh chambers or anything. I see a lot of
sandstone that's been naturally eroded
by water over hundreds of years here.
>> Well, you're right. And you know,
looking at the map, it was a very small
scale map and that dot that was put on
there and it may be on the correct spot,
it may not. You know, one of the things
I'd like to get a sense of is
how well compacted this sandstone is,
how strong it is.
Could they have tunneled through this
following fractures and maybe taking
advantage of natural,
you know, openings in the rock?
You know what I want to do is I want to
see what is holding those sand grains
together.
>> You see anything, Scott?
>> Yeah.
Seeing sand grains that
appear to have little or no cement.
That's why this stuff is pretty soft.
>> Uh-huh.
Yeah, this piece is just crumbling in my
hands.
>> Right. Right.
There's one more test that I would like
to do though.
What we have here is dilute hydrochloric
acid. I want to see if there's any
calcite cement and if it's there, it'll
fizz.
So let's see.
>> It looks like they're being absorbed
into the rock.
>> Yeah.
It's soaking in quickly, which means
there's little if any cement. It's the
open space between the sand grains.
This rock, in fact, does lend itself to
carving caves. You know, I've been to
places where I would say absolutely not,
but here I would say
it's possible.
>> So, Scott, what does it all mean?
>> Well, what it means to me is could
ancient cultures, conceivably from
Egypt, have come here to your property
and carved caves and put Egyptian
treasure in them?
Yes, I think they could have.
>> Being a realist, I'm not sure I believe
that the Russell's Cave or the mystery
tomb ever existed. And I think this
thing sort of been perpetuated by the
fact that
Southern Illinois has the nickname as
Little Egypt.
That's been around since the early
1800s. There's various things that have
that were Egyptian in them, like
the local newspaper has
pyramids on it and this picture of the
Sphinx. And then as as a coincidence,
the town at the confluence of the
Mississippi and Ohio is named Cairo.
For anybody that's come over from the
Middle East, made it all the way over
here across the Atlantic, and much less
down in Illinois, would be just the most
fantastic voyage in the history of
mankind.
>> Well, you think it's geographically
far-fetched that the Egyptians could
have come here to the heartland of
America, but I'm not ready to give up on
that idea just yet. In fact, I firmly
believe that there were many cultures
that came here prior to Columbus, going
back thousands of years. So, it's
certainly possible that the ancient
Egyptians did come here to America. We
just need to find more proof.
There are incredible stories that
ancient Egyptians somehow made their way
to what is now the United States.
But from all that I've seen, I think
that behind these legends is an
astounding truth.
At the Grand Canyon, I heard from a
descendant of some of Arizona's earliest
inhabitants about encounters with
ancient travelers from the East. It's a
story echoed by the earliest European
explorers who found clues to an Egyptian
voyage that I think the government may
be covering up.
I saw an amazing account of a
Smithsonian expedition to uncover a
wealth of Egyptian treasures hidden in
the cave large enough for 50,000 men.
Maybe the 50,000 men whom some believe
were led here by the son of Anthony and
Cleopatra.
I think the Illinois treasure cave and
the cave in the Grand Canyon could very
possibly be real.
The geology proves beyond a doubt that
ancient people could have carved hiding
places for their vast treasures in both
locations.
This great land we know as America has
many natural treasures and I'm
absolutely convinced that it's been
drawing people here for thousands of
years.